Paul Howard Ezell papers, 1939-1987
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
- Series III: Pima Land Claim Case Files, 1541-1974
  - Subseries V: Research files, 1698-1956
    The research files contain photocopies of primary source material concerning the Pima-Maricopa Indians in Arizona during the Spanish, Mexican, and American periods. The first white man to actually make contact with the Pimas and Maricopas was Eusebio Francisco Kino, a Jesuit who made four expeditions into the Gila River area between 1694 and 1699. The logs and diaries of the members of the Kino expeditions contain the first physical and cultural descriptions of the Pimas and Maricopas. Throughout the eighteenth century, there were more Spanish expeditions into the Gila River Valley. Of note are the four expeditions led by Francisco Garces from 1769-1776. The accounts of Garces and his companions Padre Pedro Font and Juan Bautista de Anza describe their contacts with the Pimas and Maricopas. When Mexico declared its independence from Spain in 1821, all of present-day Arizona came under Mexican sovereignty. During this period, there were both Mexican and American contacts with the Pimas and Maricopas. Lt. William H. Emory also made a reconnaissance of the Gila River Valley and gave a comprehensive report on the topography, flora, fauna, and peoples he encountered. In 1848, all Mexican territory north of the Gila River was ceded to the U.S., and in 1853, the land south of the Gila also became United States territory. From the time the U.S. acquired the Pima-Maricopa lands, these Indians were hosts to thousands of Americans, including California gold seekers and government agents who served as boundary commissioners and Indian agents. Such people as John Bartlett and Sylvester Mowry furnished accounts of the area during this period. The research files contain photocopies of much of the material found in the Microfilm reels, Boxes 16 and 17. English translations of many of the documents which were originally written in Spanish are also included in the files.
    - Untitled, on Southwestern Indians. No Date (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
    - Jesuit period to 1767. 1767 (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
    - Franciscans. 1767-1778 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Research files. 1780-1813 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Archivo Militar, UC Microfilm. 1821-1829 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Research files. 1841-1853 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Research files, post 1854, 1854-1910 and index. Post 1854, 1854-1910 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Research files, post 1854, 1861-1910. Post 1854, 1861-1910 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Frank Pinkley manuscript. c. 1930s (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Subseries VI: Microfilms and Audiotapes, 1646-1957
    The microfilms and audiotapes contain microfilms, reel-to-reel magnetic tapes, and a cassette tape. The five reel-to-reel magnetic tapes include Pima, Papago, Yaqui, and Mexican Indian songs, the Nedry word list of Pima and Papago words, and an interview of Cyrus Sunn, a Maricopa Indian, by Paul Ezell on 13 August 1957. The interview tells of the migration of the Maricopas from the Colorado River to the Middle Gila River area in the 1800s. Ezell's comments about the information contained on the tape can be found on page 33 of his diary from April 1957 to February 1, 1964. The cassette tape, labeled Andale, Tindale and Hayden, contains some music and a discussion of the artifacts of aboriginal tribes of Australia with Norman Tindale.
    This series also contains 24 rolls of 35 mm microfilm which contain copies of documents from the Arizona Historical Society, the Bancroft Library at the University of california, the Library of Congress, the National Archives, Archivo General de la Nacion, the Escuela Nacional de Antropologia Biblioteca, the Biblioteca Nacional Archivo Franciscano, and the Archivo General y Publico. Ezell's indexes to material on the microfilm rolls is also included. Photocopies and English translations of many of the materials on the microfilm rolls can be found in the research files.
    - Positive film rolls
      - Ezell's index to microform rolls. No Date (Box 16)
      - Roll II, Museo Nacional Biblioteca de la Escuela Nacional de Antropologia; copy of original Mex. No Date (Box 16)
      - Roll III, Archivo General de la Nacion; begins with Saldana Miguel-Table of Contents, Provincias Internas, Archivo Nacional, Mexico, D.F. No Date (Box 16)
      - Roll IV, Bancroft and University of California Libraries. No Date (Box 16)
      - Roll 1, da Civezza Collection, Vatican; inventory at beginning of roll. No Date (Box 16)
      - Roll 2, da Civezza Collection, Vatican; has list of contents on roll. No Date (Box 16)
      - Roll 3, da Civezza Collection, Vatican; has list of contents on roll. No Date (Box 16)
      - Rolls 15-27, Altar? No Date (Box 16)
      - Rolls 28-40, Altar? No Date (Box 16)
      - Arizona Sentinel; NMP 5406. October 1873 (Box 16)
      - University of California, Bancroft Library; Archivo Militar, Mexico, D.F.; documents relating to treaty Cyrus Sunn interview by Paul Ezell, 13 Aug. 1957, 2 reel-to-reel tapes Andale, Tindale and Hayden, cassette tape. No Date (Box 16)
    - Negative film rolls
      - Roll I, Pima; National Archives, Washington, D.C.; documents relating to the Pima Indians, 20 ft. No Date (Box 17)
      - Roll II, Museo Nacional, Biblioteca Nacional, 74 ft. No Date (Box 17)
      - Roll III, Archivo General de la Nacion. No Date (Box 17)
      - Roll IV, California: University Library, Bancroft Library. No Date (Box 17)
      - Roll V, Miscellaneous; Rogers-Aboriginal Cultural Relations between Southern California and the Southwest, 1941; Woodward-The Grewe Site, 1931; Triska-Hohokam; Lloyd-Aw-aw-tam Indian Nights Sonora State Archives; University of Sonora Archive: material on Pimas, Papagos, Opatas Willenbrink-Pima Dictionary, notes on Pima Indian language, 1935. University of Arizona Library, Cronica Serafica y Apostolica del Colegio de propaganda fide de la Santa Cruz de Queretaro. U.S. Dept. of the Interior. Descriptive Catalogue of Photographs of North American Indians, by W.H. Jackson. Archivo Militar, containing 1885 treaty correspondence Benjamin Thompson's calendar; Material on Father Garces from the Archives of Santa Cruz de Queretaro Father Kino Narbona and Romero, report Nedry word list, 2 reel-to-reel tapes Pima, Mexican Indian, Yaqui, and Papago songs; home recordings, 1 reel-to-reel tape. No Date (Box 17)
  - Subseries VII: Photographic Materials, 1940-1957
    The photographic materials contain 14 black and white miscellaneous photographs, most of which were taken in 1957 at places occupied by the Pima-Maricopa Indians, and 27 miscellaneous negatives. Also included are 43 color slides of Tumacacori, San Ignacio, the Kino burial, Magdalena church, Majolica, Indian dances, and 9 slides for a paper on James Ohio Pattie.
    - Photographs, 14 black and white. 1940-1957 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Negatives, 7 negatives, 7 strips 35 mm, 3 frames 35 mm. 1938-1952 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Slides, 52 color, 35 mm. No Date (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Subseries VIII: Maps, 1699-1970s
    The outstanding cartographic items are a group of nine oversize maps prepared by Paul Ezell and Alfonso Ortiz in June 1962. The maps are of the southern portion of the state of Arizona, based on the U.S.G.S. Arizona shaded relief map of 1955. They contain information concerning Pima and Maricopa place names, hunting and fishing areas, food and plant-gathering areas, Pima-Maricopa stock raising areas, miscellaneous land use areas, Pima-Maricopa territory, and Spanish exploration in the Gila-Pima area. In addition, the series contains 12 hand-drawn or traced maps. One map shows comparisons of Indian cultures and tidewater change along the Colorado River as noted by various explorers over time, ranging from Castillo in 1541 to Lumholtz in 1912. Another map is a photocopy of a reconnaissance map of the Colorado River by Major General P.F. Smith in 1851.
    Other maps include the Lower Gila River, showing historical data relating to the Maricopa Indians from 1699-1860, Garces' 1774 route, and Father Kino's explorations in Pimeria Alta. There is a road trail and developed area plan map for Organ Pipe National Monument as well as a topographical map of the Arizona-California Needles Quadrangle and other maps pertaining to the Pima Land Claim Case. Maps of Arizona and Maricopa County and a map of southern Arizona and northern Sonora drawn by Madelon Ezell in 1955 round out the collection.
    - Hand-drawn or traced maps. 1699-1943 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Maps. 1960s-1970s (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Oversize maps of Arizona containing information about the Pima and Maricopa Indians. 1962 (Box 18, Folder 6)